<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An alarum sounded in the borders of spiritual Egypt vvhich shall be heard in Babylon, and astonish the inhabitants of the defiled and polluted habitations of the earth. And the power of the Prince of Darkness called into question; and he himself examin'd by the truth, how he came to raign over mankind; and how long his time shall be, till he comes to be cast out of his dominion, and the creature be deliver'd from under his tyranny; to serve God in spirit and in truth, as Christ, the prince of peace, has order'd them. Also the number of him whom the world hath wonder'd after, found out; and demonstrated to be near at an end: and withal, that it is no wayes unlawful, nor in vain, both to hope, and to expect the utter desolation, and destruction of sin in this life, and the setting up of perfect righteousness in the souls of men, where sin has too long raign'd. Written in a testimony to the truth, and against the false position of the devil, and his servants; by a servant of God, Steven Crisp.</title>
            <author>Crisp, Stephen, 1628-1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34984</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6922</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215182</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827138</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827138</idno>
            <idno type="VID">31554</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34984)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 31554)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1846:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An alarum sounded in the borders of spiritual Egypt vvhich shall be heard in Babylon, and astonish the inhabitants of the defiled and polluted habitations of the earth. And the power of the Prince of Darkness called into question; and he himself examin'd by the truth, how he came to raign over mankind; and how long his time shall be, till he comes to be cast out of his dominion, and the creature be deliver'd from under his tyranny; to serve God in spirit and in truth, as Christ, the prince of peace, has order'd them. Also the number of him whom the world hath wonder'd after, found out; and demonstrated to be near at an end: and withal, that it is no wayes unlawful, nor in vain, both to hope, and to expect the utter desolation, and destruction of sin in this life, and the setting up of perfect righteousness in the souls of men, where sin has too long raign'd. Written in a testimony to the truth, and against the false position of the devil, and his servants; by a servant of God, Steven Crisp.</title>
                  <author>Crisp, Stephen, 1628-1692.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>47, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Devil --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Repentance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:31554:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31554:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>An ALARUM Sounded in the <hi>Borders</hi> of Spiritual Egypt, VVhich ſhall be heard in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the Inhabitants of the Defiled and Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted Habitations of the Earth.</p>
            <p>And the Power of the Prince of <hi>Darkneſs</hi> called into Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; and he himſelf Examin'd by the Truth, how he came to raign over Mankind; and how long his time ſhall be, till he come to be caſt out of his <hi>Dominion,</hi> and the <hi>Creature</hi> be deliver'd from under his <hi>Tyranny;</hi> to ſerve God in <hi>Spirit</hi> and in Truth, as Chriſt, the Prince of Peace has order'd them</p>
            <p>Alſo the Number of him, whom the world has wonder'd after, found out; and demonſtrated to be near at an End: and withal, that it is no wayes unlawful, nor in vain, both to hope, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect <hi>the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ter Deſolation, and Deſtruction, of Sin in this Life,</hi> and the ſetting up of perfect Righteouſneſs, in the ſouls of men, where Sin has too long raign'd.</p>
            <q>Written in a Teſtimony to the Truth, and against the falſe Poſition of the Devil and his Servants; by a Servant of God, <hi>Steven Criſp.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Mat. 15.12, 13, 14.</hi>
                  </bibl> Then came his Diſciples, and ſaid unto him, Know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thou that the <hi>Phariſees</hi> were offended after they heard this Saying, But he ſaid, Let them alone, they be blind Leaders of the Blind, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 John 3.8.</hi>
               </bibl> He that commits Sin, is of the Devil, &amp;c.</q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1671.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:31554:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31554:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>This ſmall <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> does not Appear with the Approbation of the Learned Doctors of this our Age; Neither do I believe, it will be received in the Accademies, or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> and among the <hi>Rabbies,</hi> whether they be <hi>Papiſts</hi> or <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> and conſidering the Subject, it is not like that it ſhould get ſuch <hi>Patrons.</hi> And therefore muſt I ſingly Recommend it, to the Witneſs of God, in thy own Conſcience, who ever thou art; by which Witneſs thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, that as long as the Devil Reigns in thee, it is not as it ought to be: And if thou be at all deſireous, that it ſhould or might be as it ought, it will be no wayes offenſive unto thee to hear of the overthrow of him, that has brought out of order; and withal, of the Appearance of him, who is the Reſtorer of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the right Heir of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this one thing I do deſire of thee, of what Profeſſion, Religion, or Judgment thou mayſt be
<pb facs="tcp:31554:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> to wit, That thou layſt by thy own Intereſt of the Controverſie (for a little time) and read without prejudice or partiallity, and be not offended, that another is not of thy Judgment; but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that thou, in thy own particular art in one and the ſame Tranſgreſſion, in the matter afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; ſeeing the greateſt part of Man-kind is not of thy Judgment; And they have as much power to Judge thee, that thou art wrong, as thou haſt to Judge me that I am wrong. Therefore read in coolneſs, and conſider what thou read'ſt; as knowing, that it is God that muſt give an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: and whereas the Subject or Matter of the Treatiſe does comprehend much, and many things are but hinted at, therefore look up to the Lord, who can enlarge thy underſtanding in it, as it pleaſeth him.</p>
            <p>And as concerning the Prieſts, who are ſo buſie to make Complaints againſt Sectarians, Hereticks, and heretical Books; deſiring the Magiſtrates, they would abuſe their Power, to defend them and their Doctrine by <hi>Perſecution:</hi> They would do better, to employ their time in the anſwering of theſe Poſitions. And whereas they are call'd Spiritual, let them fight with Spiritual Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons (if they have them) and bring forth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:31554:3"/> in defence of their old Maſter, and his Kingdom and Power, now in a time of need, when it is near come to an end.</p>
            <p>And whereas the words <hi>Government, Dominion, Raign, and Kingdom,</hi> are often us'd; by which, ſome of perverſe Minds may conclude, That I intend thereby the Overthrow, or Changing or Subvert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of outward Government. To prevent ſuch a <hi>Momus,</hi> I do declare in the ſight of God, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all Men, That I have no ſuch thought, or intention; perfectly declaring my Judgment, viz. That a Chriſtian ought to live peaceably, and quietly under all ſorts of Governments, which the Lord permits to be, or is pleaſed to ſet up; and I do believe, That the Ruling or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of an Emperor, King, Prince, or State in it ſelf, is not Repugnant to, but Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt with the Government of Chriſt, whoſe Kingdom is Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual; and the more he Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gns in the Hearts of People, the eaſier will it be for the Rulers of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s World to f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lfill their Office, and if the Devil were wholly diſ-thron'd; yet no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>withſtanding, they might ſtill Rule, De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng Juſtice, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Words of him, who ſaid, <hi>By me Kings Raign, and the Princes decree Juſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ice; by me Princes Rule, and the Nobles, even all the Judges of
<pb facs="tcp:31554:4"/> the Earth, Prov.</hi> 8.15, 16. And then they would be under him, who is their King and Lord; and the People would live a pleaſant, Godly and peaceable life, under their Reſpective Kings and Lords.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing theſe things are promiſed, and that he is faithfull that hath promiſed them; Why ſhould not we then hope for, and expect the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling thereof? And ſo, <hi>Courteous Reader,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given thee this ſhort Caution and Inſtruction, I leave thee to Read the following Diſcourſe, and Remain a Friend to thee and all Men.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:31554:4"/>
            <head>An ALARUM Sounded in the Borders of Spiritual Egypt VVhich ſhall be heard in BABYLON, and Aſtoniſh the Inhabitants of the Defiled and Polluted Habitations of the EARTH.</head>
            <p>MAny are the Devices of Satan, and great is the Subtilty which he furniſheth his Children and Servants with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al; by which he ſeeks to uphold his kingdom; pleading now a Right to that which he got by Subtilty; and has taught his whole Family, That it is impoſſible for any to be freed from under his Service; even as if all men, that are created of God, were created to the ſervice of the Devil: and although he can make no man, yet that he is able, after they are made, to keep them in his ſervice; yea, although their Maker does call for them to ſerve him: And ſo by this ſuppos'd Neceſſity (which is a Doctrine well-pleaſing to the fleſh) he keeps Nations, Kindreds, Tongues, and People in Bondage to his will; and not only ſo, but he has ſo bewitched, and beſotted his whole <hi>Synagogue,</hi> and every ſort in it, that they cannot endure to hear that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:31554:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> they ſhould be made free; and all that comes to declare Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to theſe Captives, and an opening of the Door of this Priſon-houſe <hi>(the darkneſs)</hi> unto thoſe that are ſhut up within it; they cry out againſt ſuch, Away with them from the Earth; let them be Crucified, Stoned, Hanged, Burned, Impriſoned and Baniſhed; or at leaſt, derided and mocked at, and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of evil be ſpoken of them: And what have they done? They have preached againſt Sin, that it muſt come to an end; and have preached that that which is Perfect is to be found in this life, by which men might come to the acceptable Year of the Lord, unto whom there is nothing acceptable which is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect.</p>
            <p>Certainly there is no manner of Slaves, ſo well contented with their Bondage, as the Devil's are; and therefore it is worth the conſidering, what right he has to Raign over Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and what Work it is, he gives his Servants to do, that is ſo well pleaſing unto them, that they cannot endure to hear of being ſet at liberty, as long as they have a day to live: As for my part I have conſidered; what right the Devil can claim to the Government, which he has among the Children of Men, raigning over Kings and Princes, Prieſts and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, from one Sect to another, ſetting them all to work in blind Zeal one againſt another, yet all agreeing in this one Queſtion (to wit) Is there any Man or Woman upon the Earth, that is freed from under the reign of the Devil, that he can live without Sin? or is it poſſible for any to be ſo? the general Anſwer is, <hi>No;</hi> we are all, and muſt be all his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants all the dayes of our lives. But ſome might ſay, Seeing you are all Fellow-Servants; and that both you, and your Work do belong to one Maſter, why then are you diſagreeing with one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other about the work: But Oh, my ſoul longeth that ſome might be awakened, once to conſider, and to bethink themſelves, how they came to this ſtate and condition, and by what right and authority, their Maſter keeps them in this Bondage; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not both lawfull and poſſible, to come from under it.</p>
            <p>And in the firſt place it is to be conſidered, that this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which is called the Devil and Satan, had no dominion over Man in the beginning; for God gave Man power over all
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:31554:5"/> Beaſts, Fiſhes, Fowls, and over every creeping thing, that he ſhould Rule over them; and in that time, the Devil that old creeping Serpent was kept under, and could not ſpeak, nor command as with authority, and he being but a ſubject himſelf, he ſought to have dominion; having loſt the glory of the everlaſting Kingdom, and ſo he came to the Woman, which was made and brought forth in a time of ſleep and perſwaded her, (Mark, not commanded) and his perſwaſion was; that ſhe ſhould break the Command of God; under pretence that ſhe ſhould be profited thereby: So here was but a ſneeking un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly ſpirit, coming to the Woman in a deceitful feigned manner, with a Lye in his mouth, to ſee if he could deceive her, and lead her to be diſobedient to her God and Maker; Who could then have thought, that this ſpirit, that was ſubject to all ſorts of miſery, ſhould have reigned and ruled over ſo many Millions of thouſands of Men, both high and low, young and old? Well, the Woman hearkned after a Lye, and broke the Command of God, and went to try whether this Serpent had found out a way, to make her better or not; and not only ſo, but went to the Man, and gave him alſo, and he did eat: Mark, this Devil; the old Serpent, he did not go to the Man; that was a work too high for him; but there comes his Companion, (which was given of God) which was of his Fleſh and Bones, to tempt him; he did not hearken to the Devil, but to his deceived Wife, and he did eat, and their Eyes were opened, and they were aſham'd, and hid themſelves: Here were the two firſt ſubjects which the Devil had in his Kingdom, he having before this time no Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion among the Creatures which God had made.</p>
            <p>Now it is to be obſerved, that there are but four wayes to come into Dominion; to wit, <hi>by Deſcent, by Election, by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and by Treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now which of theſe it is, by which the <hi>Devil</hi> got his entrance, is eaſie to be concluded: All that are wiſe will ſay, That it was by <hi>Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Falſhood,</hi> and that Man thereby came to be deprived of that Dominion and Rule, which he had before, and his boldneſs, was taken from him, and he was aſhamed: So now ſee for whom you are pleading, all you that are ſo zaelouſly pleading for the Devils Kingdom (viz) for an old <hi>Traytor,</hi> that came into
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:31554:6"/> his Government by a Lye, and ſpoyl'd our Predeceſſors, of their Dominion, Glory and Power at once, by Sin, for which you are now pleading: Oh, Bluſh and be aſhamed every one of you, and let your mouthes be ſtopped for ever.</p>
            <p>But now, ſeeing that it fell out ſo; What was the determination of the Lord in this matter? hearken to his Sentence: And to the <hi>Serpent</hi> he ſaid, becauſe thou haſt done ſo, thou ſhalt creep upon thy Belly, and art curſed above all Cattel; and above all the Beaſts of the Feild; ſee he muſt creep upon his Belly, and not ſtand upon his tip-toes, lifting up his head above the Nations; he muſt eat Duſt, and the other Beaſts muſt eat the Graſs of the Field; but he Duſt, all the dayes of his life, and not the Fat of the Land, and to have the tenth part of the Fruits of the Earth beſtowed on his meaneſt Servants, having alſo the other nine parts of it beſtowed and ordered to his will, and ſo ſhall it be with thee as long as thou liveſt; that is not to ſay, that he ſhall live for ever, and to have Duſt to eat, and a Belly to creep upon; But at laſt God has determined that his head ſhould be bruiſed, <hi>there is his end.</hi> Oh! All ye Pleaders for Sin, behold your Prince, and hear his Sentence and be aſham'd, and ſtop your Monthes forever.</p>
            <p>And now when he had gotten a little Dominion, let Us ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine a little, how this Trayter us'd his Rule in the beginning? his firſt Leſſon was, to Teach his new ſubjects, to hide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the preſence of God, that which before was their chiefeſt joy and crown, was now their greateſt fear and dread; and ſo they run under the Trees, hiding themſelves, as their Poſterity now does at this day; but the Lord found them out, and ſpoke to them, and cauſed them to hear that dreadfull Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; and not only ſo, but drove them out from where Life was to be found, into the Earth, where there was nothing to be gotten without pain and labour; and whereas they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in Dominion, and had nothing to do but to dreſs the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in which the Life was; they muſt now Till the Ground, which brought forth unto them Bryers and Thorns; and in that ſtate Man's miſery was great, and his ſorrow unſpeakable; and his darkneſs not to be expreſſed; and had loſt his diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of things that differ, and having an expectation of a Seed,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:31554:6"/> which ſhould deſtroy the Serpent, and bruiſe his head; he was apt to think every Birth, to be that Seed (as his Children in the fall do at this day) ſo that when <hi>Cain</hi> was born, his mother ſaid, ſhe had gotten a Man from the Lord; but poor Woman, ſhe knew not the feed, and how that that ſeed which is born of the fleſh, is a Perſecutor, and that the Enmity is great in the firſt birth; and ſo that although he grew up to be an Offerer, yet he did not grow up in dominion over the Serpent, nor over the quality of the Deſtroyer in himſelf, and that ſort of Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was more acceptable to the Devil then to God. And now mark; that man was a Sinner, and yet religious, his Sin and Religion were conſiſtant, and could have place together at one and the ſame time in one man, as it is now with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of this Age; who ſay, they are Sinners, and that their beſt Works are polluted and defiled with Sin, and that they muſt remain ſo whilſt they live; and yet they will ſeek acceptance with God in theſe poluted Offerings; notwithſtanding they do profeſs him to be pure to whom they Offer: Thus was this firſt Sacrificer blind and darkned, and ſo are many Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands after him, and the dominion of the Devil was over him.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Deceiving him, by Leading him, to Expect an Acceptance, becauſe he Offered, though with an Evil Heart.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to lead him into the evil which had kept him from acceptance.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, by making him ſo Wrath and Angry (becauſe he was not accepted) againſt his Brother that did well, and was partaker of the one ſure Faith of the Elect Seed of God: And the Serpent having thus darkned his mind, then he durſt come before him with a Lye (though he was a Man, of whom <hi>Eve</hi> thought, that ſhe had gotten him from the Lord) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading him, that if that Faithfull <hi>Abel</hi> was out of the Way, that then it would be better with him: So he hearkned to the Counſel of this evil ſpirit, and ſhed Innocent Blood about Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; here Perſecution got his entrance into the World, by one that was an Offerer, and an evil Doer together; a fit Inſtrument for ſuch a Work. But behold, what became of this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:31554:7"/> Man; the Blood which he had ſhed, and the Earth which had drunk it up, cry'd for Vengance againſt this bloody Offerer, and he fear'd exceedingly, and ſaid, He could not bear his Puniſhment; and ſaid, Every one that finds me will ſlay me; and to prevent that, he went and Built a City in the Land of <hi>Nod;</hi> hear was the beginning of Fortifications, which was to defend the Tranſgreſſor; for the Righteous have a Tower, namely, the Name of God, and there they are ſafe without ſuch Gates or Walls.</p>
            <p>Now let every one conſider, how little right this ſpirit had in all theſe things; but he entred by a Lye, and Reigned by a Lye, and Darkneſs and deceit was his defence for his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and how little reaſon there is to plead for ſuch a ſpirit, let the wiſe in heart judge.</p>
            <p>It would go beyond my preſent aime and purpoſe, to trace this ſpirit, who is called the <hi>Devil</hi> and <hi>Satan,</hi> the <hi>Dragon</hi> and old <hi>Serpent,</hi> through all Ages, ſince the beginning; to ſee with how little Truth, Right or Equity he came up, to Reign a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Men. The underſtanding Reader of the Scriptures of Truth, can ſee it clear enough; and it is a great wonder (and one of the greateſt) that is in that part of the World, called <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> that there are ſo many men (being men of knowledge in other matters, and ſuch as ſet up the Scriptures, ſo much as they ſeem to do, calling it the Word of God, the Rule of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, the Light of the World, the Guide of Life, &amp;c.) that they ſhould go with ſuch a Book in their hands, pleading for the Devil's Kingdom; and for a neceſſity that it muſt continue, as long as there is a man upon Earth: Whereas the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in ſubſtance, is nothing elſe but as a Declaration againſt him, and his Government, and ſheweth, how he ought to be forſaken, oppoſed, reſiſted, and caſt out; and withall, how that Primitive, pure and holy, and Righteous Law of that Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which is called God, and is holy, pure, and Bleſſed for ever, how that ought to be imbraced, received and exalted in the whole Creation; I ſay, this is a very great wonder, of which and of the conſequences thereof, the Chriſtians ſo called have cauſe to be aſhamed; yea, are a Reproach to the whole
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:31554:7"/> World; and it is high time that ſome do ariſe for God; and the call is gone forth, Who is on the Lord's part, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.26. The Devil has an innumerable Hoſt, to plead for Sin, ſome with Arguments, and ſome with cruel Weapons; but who is on the Lord's part, that can ſay, the Lord Reigns in Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and in Truth he Judges the Earth? Oh! All ye car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Profeſſors of God and Chriſt, in words, but in works deny him, and ſayes, that Sin muſt ſtand, and remain as long as you live. Be it known unto you, in the Name of the God of Heaven, that where Sin remains, there the Devil is Prince and Ruler: And if that muſt remain as long as you live, the Devil deſires it no longer; for he that will be his Servant in this life, muſt be his Companion in the World to come. But hear ye the Word of the Lord, thou great Hoſt, and mighty Army of the Devil, Beaſt, Serpent, and the old Deceiver, who plead that his Government ſhall ſtand as long as there is a man to live upon Earth: The Controverſie of the Lord God Almighty is Proclaimed, and begun againſt you all, and your Prince; yea, the Arm of the everlaſting God is ſtretched out againſt you, and henceforth ye ſhall not be proſperous; but the Dominion of your Prince ſhall be leſſened, and both his and your Power ſhall be weakned, and your Weapons, both of Deceit and Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty ſhall be broken and come to nought: The Inheritance of of the Wicked ſhall be laid waſte, and the deſign which hath been carried on ſo long ſhall be fruſtrated; Deceit and Falſhood ſhall fall before the Truth, and Darkneſs ſhall flee before the Light, and your fortified City ſhall fail you, and the Land of <hi>Nod</hi> will not be a hiding place for you: For the Arm of the mighty God of <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhall ſcatter you as a reproach, and make y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u aſhamed of your Work, and of your Prince.</p>
            <p>Now to touch a tittle at your Arguments, which the Servants of this ſpirit make uſe of, for to hold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p his Kingd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m; of whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h they ſay, It is impoſſible tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it ſhould be brought down; even as if God had given up all Man kind? which is the beſt of his Creation) unto t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Devil; and that he ſhould keep none of them for himſelf to ſerve him, till they have fulf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lled the Devi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'s work to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ll; and can ſerve him no longer: Certainly t e <hi>Heathens, M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ors,</hi> and <hi>Indians,</hi> have a better D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctrine then theſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:31554:8"/> in the ground, though Darkneſs is over their underſtandings, as concerning God and Heaven, and ſuch things, yet many of them, do not judge that there is ſuch a neceſſity to do evil as long as they live; but abſtain from that which they know to be evil, and they that do ſo, are eſteemed to have their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and delight in the <hi>Elizium-Feilds,</hi> after they are dead. <hi>Lucillius</hi> ſaid; know ye not what grevious Puniſhments and Torments the wicked and evil men are to ſuffer after this life; or in what great happineſs the good men ſhall live? The Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then <hi>Epicarmus,</hi> ſaid, If thou art godly in thy mind, thou ſhalt (being dead) not ſuffer evil; and many ſuch ſayings are among them: But theſe fallen Chriſtians who plead a neceſſity to ſerve this ſpirit, whom they call the Devil, whoſe place they will confeſs is in Hell, and in the everlaſting Fire; yet they notwithſtanding without doing good expect to injoy their <hi>Elizium;</hi> to wit, a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven where God and the holy Angels dwell forever.</p>
            <p>Now let us examine a little what reaſon there is for this great miſtake.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> They ſay, that <hi>Sin is rooted and planted in the Nature of Man; yea, ſo that a Man muſt ceaſe to be a Man, before he can come to ceaſe from being a Sinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> That Man in his Natural ſtate, is ſo united with Sin as that he thereby is ſeperated from God, I do not deny; and alſo that there is a natural inclination in man, to commit <hi>Sin,</hi> is alſo true; to wit, as long as they remain in their natural ſtate and condition: And if theſe Champions for the Devil's Kingdom had blotted out (out of that which they call their Rule) all thoſe Pretious ſayings, that make mention of a ſtate of <hi>Grace,</hi> of being under <hi>Grace,</hi> of being <hi>Changed</hi> or <hi>Tranſlated,</hi> of being <hi>Redeemed</hi> and made <hi>Free,</hi> of being <hi>Waſhed, Clenſed, Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, perfectly in Soul Body and Spirit;</hi> and many more ſuch places; then they had had a <hi>Plea</hi> for their <hi>Prince:</hi> But ſeeing there is ſuch a large Teſtimony of the Mercy and goodneſs of God, and of his Power and Al-ſufficiency to Redeem and Save; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is worthy to be pleaded, before we allow the Devil ſuch an unlimitted Power in and among, yea, over all the Sons and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:31554:8"/> Daughers of Men. And therefore, as concerning the firſt part of this Objection, to wit; That Sin is rooted in the Nature of Man; How came it to be rooted there? Whoſe Work was it to make it ſo? was it the Work of God? or hath he ordered it, that it ſhould be ſo? If ſo, Why is any Man or Woman puniſhed or condemned for its being ſo, ſeeing it could not be otherwiſe? But none elſe but ſuch as are wholly blind from a true ſence of God will dare to ſay ſo: For then the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold calling of Sinners unto Repentance, to <hi>Waſh</hi> them, to <hi>Cleanſe</hi> them, to put away the <hi>Evil from them, to Ceaſe to do Evil,</hi> &amp;c. muſt all be againſt his will and ordering; and ſo conſequently but a mockery: But God forbid that any Man ſhould ſay or think ſo. Well, if it was not by the ordering or appointment of God, but that God has made Man Righteous in his Nature, Will and Affections; yea in the Image of God he Created him: Then it muſt needs be another that has wrought this great Work, to plant Sin in his Nature; and when it is examined, it will appear, that it is the work of a curſed Out-caſt, an Unclean, Lying, Treacherous Spirit, who was rejected of God, and had no place in the whole Creation, but by framing a lye he brought a poor Woman from her Integrity and Obedience; and ſo from that came a great alteration to be in her, and a Ground or Foundation was laid for the Devil to build upon; and from that time he has alwayes had a Rule in the hearts of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Diſobedience: But now that this Rule and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould not onely be Univerſal, but alſo Irreſiſtable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alterable; yea, though God Almighty ſtretch forth his Power, to Redeem any out of this Kingdom, to bring them into the Kingdom of his dear Son; yet they ſay, it is impoſſible for him, till he dies. It is as much, as to ſay, If God will have any Man to ſerve him perfectly, he muſt firſt kill him, and then he ſhall have him to his ſervice in another World: Oh Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Ignorance of the Power of God, and of the end for which Chriſt came into the World! namely, to deſtroy the Divel and his Works. Now when his Work is deſtroyed, which has a tendancy to corrupt man's nature; then the nature, of Men and Women come to be ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in holy, clean and pure, and Man comes to be Reſtored to his firſt Image, and the Glory of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:31554:9"/> firſt Body is again known, of which all the Bond-ſlaves of the Devil are Ignorant; and this Power to reſtore the nature of Man again, is the Lord's alone, it was the Devil that corrupted it, and it is God that ſanctifies it again, and delivers it by the Spirit of Judgment and of Burning, which the Hypocrites can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bear.</p>
            <p>Now the manner how, the nature of Man came to be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, you have heard that it was by Man's joyning with that ſpirit, that was fallen and caſt out from God, and had onely a power in the Darkneſs, and could not Reign over any thing, but over that which he could draw from the Glory of God into the Darkneſs: And God who dwells in the Light, being moved with infinite compaſſion, ſent his Eternal Son, that was with him before the World was, that he ſhould be made partaker of the ſame nature in which Man was Created; that by the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the Eternal Power he might reſtore him unto God; and might miniſter unto the ſpirits of all ſuch, to whom this Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and corrupted ſtate was as a Priſon-houſe; And this Jeſus received not the nature of Angels, that was not his Work, but he received the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> which was in Captivity, that he might Redeem it from Captivity through Death, ſuffering under the weight of that which oppreſſed the Creature, and cauſed it to groan after Redemption; ſo that although it could not deliver it ſelf, yet it might come to be Delivered through Faith in him who is mighty to ſave; And this Jeſus which was of the Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> after the fleſh, purifieth the nature of all thoſe that joyn with him; for the Work of the Devil is to bring in corruption, and the Work of Chriſt is to deſtroy it, and inſtead thereof to bring in Everlaſting Righteouſneſs: Now where Sin is remaining in the nature; there the Covenant with Hell and Death is not broken, neither are ſuch in Covenant with God, but are yet under the Power of the Prince of the Air, whatever they may profeſs, And the death of Chriſt is yet of no value unto them, becauſe they are yet in their Sin, and corrupted nature, unchanged, Untranſlated; So that thoſe that hold this Plea for the Devil, that <hi>becauſe he once got a Place in the nature of Man, and has corrupted it; that therefore Sin muſt remain ſo long as the Life or nature remains,</hi> ſuch are ſtrangers to the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:31554:9"/> Work of God, and to his Power by which he worketh, and alſo to Chriſt Jeſus, through whom he works; and they have more Faith in the Power of the Devil, then in the Power of Chriſt, believing that the Devil is more able to keep the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and to hold faſt that, which by Deceit, and Treachery he has gotten in it; then God (who made the Creature good in his nature) is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble, to reſtore it to his firſt purity, that the Creature might come to ſerve him in Righteouſneſs and Holineſs; And ſuch as ſo believe, are no true Chriſtians, nor true Believers: But are ſtanding in the corrupt nature, that has unity with the Devil and plead his Cauſe, who is willing, that his corrupt birth ſhould live in Man, as long as he lives in the World; For he knows that ſo long no acceptable Sacrifice can be offered up to God; for you cannot bring forth a clean Sacrifice out of an unclean Veſſel; and as long as nature is defiled; the works will be unclean, that are wrought in that nature.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The ſecond pleading is; <hi>That never any Man was freed from Sin, ever ſince Sin firſt entred into the World; and that therefore it is Preſumption, to expect ſuch a thing in this Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. If this Poſition were true; That there was never any Man freed from Sin; yet it would be preſumption to ſay, that God ſhould not be able to do that, which he never did: and it is alſo preſumption to conclude, that never any Man was freed; but if this Poſition be falſe, then not only the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is falſe, to wit, that none can be freed, but alſo the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument it ſelf is proved to be a Lye, and ſo is ſwept away, and a Door is opened unto all, that has more love to Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, then to Sin, both to hope and to expect, that the ſame work ſhould again be wrought in and for them, without preſumption. Now, that all men are Sinners by nature, is evident; and that ſome were changed out of that natural State, is as evident; ſo that the Queſtion is only; whether thoſe, that are tranſlated out of that ſinfull nature, remain ſinfull, yea or nay? which if it be ſo, what advantage have they beyond others, if they, after they are tranſlated; muſt remain unfreed? But I anſwer,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:31554:10"/> with the words of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.1. <hi>He that hath ſuffered in the fleſh; hath ceaſed from Sin.</hi> And here he ſpoke of ſuch that were yet in the Body; but had ſuffered with, and were made partakers of the Sufferings and Death of Chriſt, which was to Sin; through which every one muſt paſs, before they can come to the Reſurrection, that is in Chriſt, by which (ſaid <hi>Peter) They obtained the anſwer of a good Conſcience in the Sight of God;</hi> which he calls the <hi>Baptiſm that Saves:</hi> now, ſome having been Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of that Death, Baptiſm, and Reſurrection of Chriſt, by which they came to ceaſe from Sin, and to have an anſwer of a good Conſcience, without offence both to God and Man, (which none that ſins, can have) then may there ſome lawfully expect to come to the enjoyment of the ſame ſtate of freedom and clearneſs, as well now, as formerly without preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I anſwer with the words of the Apoſtle <hi>John,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.9. <hi>He that is born of God ſinneth not; becauſe his ſeed abideth in him; and he cannot ſin, for he is born of God.</hi> Now whereas there have been ſome, that were born of God, and have been his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; and that they that were ſo, had overcome the Wicked one, ſo that he could not touch them; but they had kept their Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments white and unſpotted; and that ſome have been freed from the Law of Sin and Death; and that ſome have Walked un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mable, and without ſpot, and had put off the old Man with his Deeds, and had known the new Birth, and could by the Holy Spirit call God, Father; which things are all manifeſt in the Scriptures of Truth, which none can deny, but thoſe, that will deny the Scripture; Why then ſhould any man queſtion, that the ſame Works of Redemption ſhould not now again be brought to paſs? And therefore it is lawfull to expect it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out preſumption. This Argument being confuted by the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Saints.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Faith of Gods Elect is but one in all Ages; and that Faith has purified the Hearts of many in former Ages, and has taught them to Walk with God; as for Inſtance, <hi>Enoch</hi> Walked with God ſeveral hundreds of years:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.21.</note> and it would be a horrible thing to ſay, that he Walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with God, when he Walked in Sin; as if God Walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:31554:10"/> in a Sinfull Way: for the Prophet ſaid; the Bloody-man, nor the Worker of Iniquity Dwells nor walks not with the Lord: But <hi>Enoch</hi> Dwelled and Walked with the Lord, and did not Iniquity; for if he had, he ſhould not have obtained a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, that he pleaſed the Lord: for Sinners and Evil-doers do not pleaſe him. By Faith <hi>Noah</hi> Walked with God, and was a Preacher of Righteouſneſs in the old World;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5.</note> alſo <hi>Lot</hi> in <hi>Sodom:</hi> which they could not have been, if they had been Sinners, except they had been ſuch Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as the Preachers at this day; but they were owned of God, though they were mocked of men; and it is ſaid of them, that they did Inherit Righteouſneſs which they preached: And of <hi>Lot</hi> it is ſaid, that his Soul as well as his Doctrine was Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous: And by the ſame Faith <hi>Job</hi> was kept in the fear of God in the Land of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>z;</hi> for that taught him to eſchew evil, by which he obtained a Teſtimony of God, that he was perfect and upright; which no Sinner is:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Job</hi> 1.22.</note> and if he had not been free from Sin, it would have been falſe to ſay of him; that he eſchewed the evil, and was perfect: and though his Tryals were many; yet he ſinned not with his Lips, neither did he charge God fooliſhly, and in the end of all his Tryals God cleared him of having ſinned, witneſſing, that he had found him faithfull, and received a Sacrifice from his Hand for thoſe zealous Profeſſors, that had charged him with Sin, whom God had cleared: And the ſame Faith cauſed <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Sarah</hi> to be partakers of the Promiſe; and <hi>Abraham</hi> was a Friend of God, of which Chriſt ſaid, That none could be, but by fulfilling his Will; and thoſe that do ſo, are no Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: And by this Faith <hi>Moſes</hi> chuſed rather to ſuffer Affliction with the People of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.25.</note> then to enjoy the pleaſures of Sin: So mark, he left Sin and the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of it, and then he muſt be without Sin; by which he obtained a Teſtimony, that he was a Servant of God, which Sinners are not. By Faith <hi>David's</hi> Heart was made after the Mind of God, and that is not ſinfull, but free from it, for in him is no Darkneſs at all. By the ſame Faith the Prophets were choſen Veſſels of God, and were upheld in their Teſtimony for God, till they came to obtain that Teſtimony,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:31554:11"/> that they were the Men and Servants of God, which they could not have been, and withall Servants unto Sin; And the Scripture beareth Record of <hi>Zachariah</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> his Wife,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 1.2.</note> that they were both Righteous before God, not by an Imagined Righteouſneſs; but in regard to their Couverſation, walking in all the Commands and Statutes of the Lord unblamable; but if they had been under the Power of Sin, and not freed from it; they had been neither unblamable, nor Righteous, but muſt at leaſt have Tranſgreſſed ſome of the commands of the Lord, or elſe they could not be Sinners. Alſo <hi>Nathaniel,</hi> in whom there was no Guile, which could not have been,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 1.48.</note> if he had been under the Power of Sin; And much more might I write upon this Subject, to ſhew, how that many by this one Faith in all Ages have been delivered from Sin, and become the Children and Servants of God; and therefore thoſe, that are Partakers of this Faith in this Age, may hope and expect, that the ſame Work may be wrought in them; and this is no preſumption: And if theſe Sin-pleaders ſhould ſay, that there is none Partaker of this Faith now at this day, and therefore cannot be made free from Sin, they will exclude themſelves, which they will hardly do, becauſe they would fain have a Name of being Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, though they deny the Work of the True Faith in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>Further, let us conſider, what theſe ſtrong Pleaders for Sin have to fortifie themſelves withall; They ſay, <hi>they have the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to plead withall for Sin;</hi> which certainly was never the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the holly Spirit, by which it was given forth: But (ſay They) It is written in 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.46. <hi>For here is no Man that ſinneth not.</hi> Anſw. This is very true, neither do I plead, that any man is free from Sin all the dayes of his life (except Chriſt) but have confeſſed, they are all Sinners by nature, untill they be changed: and beſides, there it is but ſpoken of a People, that were under the Law, of which the Apoſtle ſayes, that it made nothing perfect; but, ſaid he, the bringing in of a better Hope did; but the <hi>Law</hi> did not purifie the Comers thereunto, according to the Conſcience: but, when the Offerers had offered, there remained an Evidence of Sin in the Conſcience; but what is that to the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:31554:11"/> Chriſtians, who are come to know a better Hope, and the Blood that purifieth the Conſcience; for that ſame Apoſtle that ſaid, the <hi>Law</hi> made no man perfect (under which <hi>Law Solomon</hi> was, as alſo that People, concerning whom it was ſaid; there is none that lives and ſinneth not) notwithſtanding the ſame Apoſtle ſaid, that it was the bringing in of a better Hope, that did it: And what are theſe Fighters for Sin, and Sin-pleaders become ſo Zealous, that they will rather deny the better Hope then to ceaſe from Sin? if not, then there is a poſſibillity to be made perfect by the Blood of Chriſt, which the Blood of Bulls and Goats could not do.</p>
            <p>An other Objection is brought forth; that is, <hi>That the Apoſtle</hi> Paul <hi>ſaid, that Sin lived in him, and that the good that He would do, He did not; and the evil that He would not do, that He did.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. That <hi>Paul</hi> knew the paſſing through ſuch a State, is without queſtion, and is not denied; but this does not prove at all, that he never knew no better State; or that he never came to perfection; for in that place he makes mention of three States. Firſt, How it was with him, when he lived without the <hi>Law</hi> of God in his liberty to fight againſt the Truth; and he thought, he might do many things againſt the Name of Jeſus. Secondly, He declares of his Convincement, and how it was with him then, when he knew, he ſhould not do no more againſt the Truth, and yet, not being wholly changed he did things which he knew he ought not, by reaſon of Sin living and dwelling in him; and that State he did not call Happy or Bleſſed (as theſe blind Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors do at this day, that takes up a Reſt in this State, and ſay, they can never be Redeemed out of it (for he ſpeaking of ſuch a Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, cryes out for Deliverance, calling it a miſerable Condition, which plainly ſheweth, that his eye was upon a further and better State, unto which he alſo beareth Witneſs; ſaying, he was made free by the Law of the Spirit of Life both of the Law of Sin and of Death; in which time he was yet in the Body.</p>
            <p>Now, what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſon have theſe Pleaders for Sin to believe, that <hi>Paul</hi> was in all theſe three States at once? and if not; Why not
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:31554:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> in the laſt? being the other two are but fore-going States, leading to the third; eſpecially conſidering the many other Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, which he gives of his being perfect; and of thoſe, that by his Miniſtry were brought to perfection; ſaying, concerning himſelf, <hi>Timothy,</hi> and <hi>Silvanus: We can do nothing againſt the Truth:</hi> and in an other place he teſtifies, <hi>That he has fought a good Fight, kept the Faith, and finiſhed his Courſe.</hi> Now if it was finiſhed, then there was no more to run: and if the Fight was Fought; then the Enemies were no more alive, as they were, when Sin lived and dwelled in him. Again he ſayes in an other place; <hi>We preach Wiſdom among them that are Perfect:</hi> That is after the explication and Sence of theſe Sin-pleaders; We preach Wiſdom among none, except among thoſe, that are already departed out of this World, and gone to Heaven. And again, <hi>As many of you as are Perfect, be ſo minded:</hi> That is to ſay, after their explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; let none be thus minded, before they be dead. Again at laſt, <hi>Dear Brethren be perfect; And of one mind,</hi> &amp;c. But this, they ſay, cannot be in this Life. And again he ſayes to the <hi>Hebrews; You are come to the ſpirits of juſt Men made perfect, and to God the Righteous Judge of all,</hi> &amp;c. But where were theſe <hi>Hebrews?</hi> were they yet alive, or were they dead? if dead; How came his Epiſtle to meet them? But a wilfull Blindneſs is come over ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe Servants and Miniſters of Darkneſs, and they have rebellious Hearts againſt the Light, that diſcovers their Sin, and would lead them out of it.</p>
            <p>But becauſe they have more love to Sin, then to the Light; therefore they ſeek to cover themſelves ſo much: But the Day is come, that has diſcovered them, and their deceitfull Coverings will not longer cover them.</p>
            <p>An other pleading is of that which is ſpoken by the Apoſtle, <hi>John</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.8. <hi>If we ſay we have no Sin, we deceive our ſelves, and the Truth is not in us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Out of which words every miſerable, and pitifull Souldier of this great Prince of Darkneſs thinks, he may Arm himſelf ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently to fight againſt that, which would deliver them and make them free: But if this Scripture were ſeen and read with that Spirit
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:31554:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> by which, and in which it was written; then it would appear, that this <hi>John</hi> was not ſuch a great Friend to Sin, and the Devil (who is a Father of Lyes) as they would have him to be; For in the ſame Chapter he had ſhewed before, into what State they muſt come, before they can come to have Fellowſhip with God, viz. To walk in the Light, as Chriſt was in the Light: and thoſe that ſaid, They had Fellowſhip with God and Chriſt, (as the Prieſts and Profeſſors do at this day) and did not come to attain unto that State to walk in the Light, but inſtead thereof walked in Darkneſs; ſuch ſaid he, were Lyars, and did not the Truth.</p>
            <p>Now he ſaid; his Fellowſhip was with the Father and with the Son; which could not be, if he had walked in Darkneſs, or was a Sinner, or that he had not walked in the Light, as Chriſt was in the Light, for then he would have made himſelf a Lyar, if he had been a Sinner, when he ſaid; that he had Fellowſhip with God and Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And therefore it ought to be well obſerved, that <hi>John</hi> ſpeakes there of a ſort of Men, that were not yet brought to confeſs their Sins; and if ſuch came to that Conceit and Pride, as to ſay, they had no Sins to confeſs; and ſo exalted themſelves above the Witneſs of God that reproved them; then ſuch deceived themſelves: But if theſe that are ſo ſinfull, come to own that which brings them to a Confeſſion of their Sins; then God is Faithfull to forgive ſuch their Sins, and to Cleanſe them from all Iniquity. Now, when this is done, to wit; when the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture has confeſſed his Sin, and God has forgiven it, and Cleanſed him; What muſt then that Man ſay? Muſt he then ſay; that he has his Sin ſtill, when he has it not? Muſt he ſay, that he is Fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and Defiled, when he is Cleanſed from all that? This would be a Lye; and If he ſhould be Cleanſed from all Sin; he muſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be Cleanſed from Lyes: And if it was his Duty to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Work of the Devil, when it was ſtanding in him, which were his Sins; May not he now being Cleanſed, confeſs God's Work that has Cleanſed him; he being Cleanſed by him free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? Muſt he therefore be cryed out of for a Deceiver and Heretick? Who is ſo blind, that cannot ſee, that it is as ſerviceable as need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and as lawfull for a man, that has known the Power of God to clenſe him, to confeſs that, and to bear a teſtimony to that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:31554:13"/> work; as it is needfull and lawfull, when the Devil's work is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted in him; to confeſs that, and to bear a Teſtimony againſt that.</p>
            <p>Yet ſaith <hi>John</hi> to thoſe that were thus waſhed: <hi>If we ſay, that we have not ſinned, we make God a Lyar;</hi> It is as much, as if he would ſay, That even thoſe that are ſaved, muſt confeſs to the Power of God, by which they have been judged for ſin; and not to exalt themſelves above it, as if they had never ſinned; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Witneſs of God teſtifieth in all, that they have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and come ſhort of the Glory of God; So that now the underſtanding Reader may ſee, that <hi>John</hi> hath not written here of an impoſſibility of being Delivered from Sin, but abſolutely the contrary; Namely, that thoſe that cannot ſay that they are without ſin, may come by confeſſing their ſins to be Cleanſed and made free from it; yea, from all that which is Unrighteous: Yet ſome will ſay, that the Apoſtle in that place uſeth the word <hi>We,</hi> as if he included himſelf; as if he would ſay at that time; if I ſhould ſay, that I had no ſin, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Anſw. This is no proof at all, becauſe the contrary is prov'd before; to wit, that he had Fellowſhip with God and Chriſt, which no Man could have that walked not in the Light, as he is in the Light, and ſuch may as well, by the ſame manner of ſpeaking, prove <hi>James</hi> to be a Curſer; whereas he ſaid, with the Tongue we Bleſs God, and with it we Curſe Men that are made after the Image of God; and many more ſuch Inſtances might be brought forth, of the Lamentations and Complaints of the Prophets concerning the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which is Tranſlated ſo in that manner of ſpeaking, which does not prove at all, that the Prophets were Guilty of ſuch Sin and Rebellion, of which they complained, <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.37. &amp;c. But how zealous are theſe Pleaders for ſin to find out words, which, they think, do ſerve for the upholding of the Kingdom of their Maſter, when there is not one word, that properly belongs, or was written to their purpoſe, except that Part of it, which the Devil and his Servants, their Predeceſſors has Spoken or Written, and that indeed may ſerve them; as I once heard a Prieſt, that was exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the People to imploy their Time, and Ability to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knowledge, confirming his Exhortation with the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:31554:13"/> (viz.) <hi>Gen.</hi> 5. <hi>You ſhall be as Gods, knowing Good and Evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And an other, a <hi>Menniſt Preacher</hi> in <hi>North-Holland,</hi> whilſt he was warning the People to take heed of being Deceived, he exhorteth them to Immitate the deaf <hi>Adders, Pſal.</hi> 58.4. <hi>And ſo to ſtop their Bars againſt the voice of the Charmers, that charm never ſo wiſely:</hi> So, the one hath his Proof from the <hi>Adders,</hi> and the other from the Devil. Such Scripture Places as theſe, I do confeſs, that theſe Pleaders for Sin may find to ſtrengthen their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; but that which was written by the Motion of the Holy Spirit of God, is a perfect Teſtimony againſt them all; againſt their Work, and againſt their Prince.</p>
            <p>So, having anſwer'd their chiefeſt Objections, which they draw out of the Scripture; by which they endeavour to prove, <hi>That none can be free from ſin in this life,</hi> contrary to <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.22. I make haſte to the third great Argument of theſe Captives, which they lay down againſt their own Freedom:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That is, <hi>That it is the Will of God, to let ſome Sins remain in the Best of his People, to keep them Humble thereby.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If it be the Will of God, that his beſt Servants ſhould ſin; then his Will is done, when they ſin. And what reaſon have any men to be humbled and caſt-down, becauſe they have done the Will of God? but rather to rejoyce, and be glad, that the Will of God is done, and that their Will is conformable to the Will of God, that the Will of both can be done together: This is a very eaſie way to the Joy of the Lord, if this brings to tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſentence, <hi>Well done Good and Faithful Servant, &amp;c.</hi> But Wo unto thoſe, that are given up to believe this Lye.</p>
            <p>Again, Let the underſtanding Reader (I mean thoſe, that are weary with their ſins, and are willing to be freed) conſider, (for, as concerning the other, they are my Oppoſers) How can God properly be call'd <hi>Almighty?</hi> and how can the Work of the Converſion of Souls properly be call'd <hi>His,</hi> if he is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitated to borrow ſomething from the Devil to keep his Children Humble withal? Certainly we muſt conclude, That if God had a better way to do it, that he would do it in the beſt, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:31554:14"/> not in the worſt way, <hi>viz.</hi> By Sin; which is ſo very contrary to his nature.</p>
            <p>But, Let but theſe Sin-Pleaders ſuppoſe, That if God ſhould ſtretch forth his Power ſo far in man, that it ſhould deſtroy all the Works of the Devil, and caſt out Sin; and cauſe his Soul to take as great Delight and Joy in Well-doing, as ever it had in Sin; and ſhould plant Humility as naturally in the Soul, as the Devil has planted Pride in it.</p>
            <p>Now the Queſtion is, <hi>Whether this Power, that works this change, be not as able to keep the Creature in this Condition, as to bring him to it, without any help of the Devil or his Work?</hi> But they will ſay, <hi>To ſuppoſe a thing that is Impoſſible, is either against Reaſon, or Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I Anſwer,</hi> All things are Poſſible with God, except to Lye; and as concerning this, It is not only poſſible, but the contrary is impoſſible, becauſe God hath ſo often promis'd it, to make a perfect Work, and to finiſh his Work in all them that truſt in him: And for this End is Chriſt Jeſus come, <hi>That he might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Devil, and his Works:</hi> And in the Parable he ſaith, <hi>When he comes, that is ſtronger, he ſhall bind the ſtrong Man, and ſpoil his Goods, and cast him out.</hi> This ſeems as if Chriſt, who is the ſtronger, had no need of the Devil, or his Goods either, to keep his People Humble thereby: But the Apoſtle ſaid, That they were kept by Faith through the Power of God, unto Salvation: Except you will ſay, as the Prieſts in <hi>Scotland</hi> ſay, <hi>Curſed is he that ſayes, Faith it without Sin; and let all the People ſay, Amen.</hi> Then the words of the Apoſtle muſt be read thus, You are kept by a Faith, which is mixed with ſin, in the Power of God unto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: But if you will have it ſo, ſpeak it out, as they have done; but, being you profeſs, That Faith is the Gift of God; we may well ſay, It is able to clenſe the Heart, and to give Victory over the World, and alſo over the Devil, and Sin; and then there is no need of ſin, to keep us Humble: For if Humility was a Fruit of ſin, it would not be ſo acceptable unto God, as it is; for the Prophet ſays, <hi>He giveth his Grace to the Humble, and dwelleth with ſuch that are of a Contrite and Broken Heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:31554:14"/>
            <p>Again, if a few ſins, yea, though they be but a Remnant, can keep men Humble; then a great deal of ſin muſt needs make a man more Humble: ſo, then let us plentifully ſin, that we may plentifully be Humble. But, God forbid that ſuch doctrine or ſuch Teachers ſhould go unreprov'd; for, they have exalted the work of the Devil beyond the Work of God: And it is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch Teachers have been countenanc'd, that the People have been led into ſo much Blindneſs, Ignorance, and Hardneſs of Heart; and that People have wholly loſt the Hope and Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Day of Deliverance; and have taken up a Reſt in a ſinful and ſlaviſh ſtate.</p>
            <p>And now, If any come to Preach the Goſpel, which brings Deliverance and Freedom to the Soul, their Souls being in a Reſt already (though a Falſe Polluted Reſt) ſuch are look'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as Diſturbers of their Reſt, and Breakers of their Peace, and ſuch like; even as it was with the Prophet <hi>Micah,</hi> when he cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out (<hi>Mic.</hi> 2.10.) <hi>Ariſe ye, and depart; for this is not your Rest, becauſe it is polluted: it ſhall deſtroy you, even with a ſore De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Bleſſed be the Lord God of Heaven and Earth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, for he hath brought forth his Day of Salvation, which many have long'd after, and are longing, and are in travel that they might come to know it; to whom a ſinful ſtate is no Reſting-place, but is unto them as a ſtrange Land, in which they cannot ſing the Songs of <hi>Sion;</hi> but ſtill have <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance which is Free-born from above; longing after the Day of Gathering, that the Lamb (and not the changeable Prieſts and Teachers) may be their Light and Leader: Unto ſuch I ſay, and teſtifie in the Name of the God of Heaven, Lift up your Heads, for the Day of your Redemption draweth nigh, and Deliverance ſhall come out of <hi>Sion,</hi> the City of our Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: Iſa. 33.20. <hi>And a Mighty Voice ſhall be ſounded forth from the holy Mountain, from the Lord of Hosts, and thoſe that hear it, ſhall live; and the dead Bones in the Valleys ſhall be enliven'd: and the Joy of that Day ſhall be greater then the Joy of the Harveſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, How, and in what manner, theſe things will be brought to paſs, is a great Diſpute among many, that are yet ſeeking in the carnal Wiſdom to conceive and comprehend ſpiritual things,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:31554:15"/> and ſo they come to be ſcatter'd &amp; divided in their imaginations: And therefore in the mean time, thoſe that are become willing to ſit down in Quietneſs, in the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, that ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth every running-out of the Mind, they come to feel the Pure Fear of God to be planted in their Hearts: ſo that they dare not think their own Thoughts, nor ſpeak their own Words: And here is the beginning of the true Wiſdom, by which Wiſdom it is given unto them to underſtand thoſe things which they could not find out in all the time of their Travel and Pains in the faln Wiſdom.</p>
            <p>And whil'ſt they were hearkening after the different Voices of men, they never could have a Certainty: But now hearing him, by whom God ſpeaketh, who is manifeſt within them, whom their Ear is inclin'd unto within; they come to know certainly that which they know, through the Teſtimony of the Holy Spirit, who alone is able to reveal (unto thoſe that Fear Him) the Myſteries of God's Kingdom; and he ſhuts them up from the Wiſe and Prudent of this World.</p>
            <p>And therefore you that deſire to have an underſtanding of theſe things, come down from your high Builded Towers of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Comprehenſion; and ſit down in that Pure Light, that brings a Death upon the Earthly Wiſdom, and become as Fools, that you may be wiſe; and that Wiſdom that is ſo recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, ſhall lead to know the Number of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> which the whole World with all their <hi>Accademical Wiſdom,</hi> and all the Sects with their Inventions are ſtrangers unto at this day, and are carrying about with them his Name, and the number of it, or his Mark, by which they are accepted among Men, and yet do not know what it is: But when they come to a wiſe enough to know it, and honeſt enough to forſake it; then they will ſee, that the Friend-ſhip of this World comes to be broken, and the Enmity to work againſt the Holy Seed: and the Seed comes to ariſe and bruiſe the Head of the Enmity, and to nail it faſt to a Croſs, till it Dye; and then comes Freedom, then there is War no more, then there is peace on Earth, and nothing but good will towards all Men; yea to Enemies: Then Anguiſh and Sorrow flyeth away, and the perfect Love of God caſts out fear, and there is Death no more; but that which is overcome
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:31554:15"/> by Immortality: Bleſſed and Happy are all they that come to know that ſtate, and Bleſſed are they, that Believe and waits to enjoy it; and Bleſſed is that Hope, which leads there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
            <p>Now, as concerning the chiefeſt matter of this <hi>Treatiſe</hi> (to wit) <hi>Concerning the Reign of the Devil among Men;</hi> there is yet one thing worthy to be conſidered, of which there is made mention in the Scriptures of Truth, in which it appears, that in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and ſetting up of the Reign of Chriſt, and that the Everlaſting Goſpel was Preached, and that many Thouſands had Believed and Obeyed it, ſo that they came to be Witneſſes of the Kingdom of Chriſt; and that the Devil was caſt out, Diſ-throned and put under their Feet; and ſome were made Prieſts and Kings to God: I ſay, after all theſe things aforeſaid there came an Apoſtacy from the Faith by which all theſe things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned were brought forth; and of that Apoſtacy <hi>Paul</hi> Propheſied to the <hi>Theſſalonians;</hi> and <hi>John</hi> by the Spirit ſaw, how that the Devil ſhould get a great Dominion over Men by many changable Means and Wayes executing his Power, as a <hi>Dragon;</hi> then as a ſtrange <hi>Beaſt with ſeven Heads, and ten Horns;</hi> at an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other time, as a little <hi>Beaſt with two Horns;</hi> then with an <hi>Image;</hi> and then with a <hi>Whore</hi> &amp;c. And that the Almighty God has ſet and appointed a Time, a certain Time; to this Dreadfull, Dark, changable Government; And has given <hi>John</hi> to know, that it ſhould laſt and continue but <hi>One Thouſand Two Hundred and Threeſcore Days, or Years:</hi> And this is a ſet Time, and hath its beginning, and its ending; but the Kingdom of Chriſt, and alſo his Prieſt-hood, are both after the power of an endleſs Life.</p>
            <p>Now, ſeeing, that this laſt Power, which the Devil has gotten, is but to continue his appointed time: Why ſhould any be his Friend ſo far, as to ſay, that it muſt continue always, and that it muſt never come to an end; and that People no ways can get freedom from under his Tyrannical Power? Certainly theſe Men, that plead ſo ſtrongly for his continual Reign, and Power, have more Reaſon and Underſtanding, then they uſe: As for inſtance, ſuppoſe that one had hired a Houſe, or Farm of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:31554:16"/> another for ſeveral Years, and the Years being come to an end, that Man to whom that Houſe or farm belongeth, has a deſire to live in it himſelf: And the In-dweller not being will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and they both ſhould come to one of theſe Sin-pleaders, to hear his judgment, and determination: I believe they would ſoon ſay to the In-dweller, thou muſt depart; the other is the Land-lord, and thou haſt had thy full Time, and he now deſiring to have his Houſe, he muſt have it; and eſpecially if the In-dweller was come into the Houſe as a Thief in a dark Night, and had kept it by Violence, and had brought no profit to the Land-lord at all. And this is properly the Cauſe between God, and this Prince of Darkneſs; for he has poſeſſed the Inheritance of God, and Ruled over it; not to the advantage of the Lord; But to his diſadvantage and diſhonour: And yet theſe Men will not do ſo much right to God, as they will do to their Neigbour. But on the contrary they ſay; that this Uſurper, or Thief, that has ſtolen away the Hearts of Men from their Creator, muſt ſit there as long, as there is a Man upon the Earth, and not any Man Redeemed. Oh! Bluſh for ſhame, ye Hypocrites; can you make a difference between Good, and Evil among Men; and will you not judge for God? Come, take your Books into your Hands, and read the number of the Years, it is called 1260. Days; reckon after the reckoning of the Ancients 30. days to a Moneth; and ſee whether that does not make out 42. Moneths, and ſee whether 42. Moneths does not make a Time, Times, and half a Time; and ſee what things are ordered to be in thoſe different Times; and ſee, whether you can find out the beginning of thoſe Times, that ſo you may find the end of them; for all thoſe, that had their confidence in the Number of the Year, 1666. are now Confounded, Aſhamed, and their Hope is fruſtrated: And now it is high time to wait upon the Lord, to get an Underſtanding, and Knowledge which makes not aſhamed.</p>
            <p>Now, the firſt thing to be conſidered, to the opening of this thing is: That the firſt appearance of this Man Child, that was Born in Heaven by a Woman, that was cloathed with the Son; and had her Feet upon the Moon, and was Crowned
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:31554:16"/> with the Stars. The firſt I ſay, that appeared againſt this Child, was a great red <hi>Dragon:</hi> Mark, this was no <hi>Subſtitute</hi> under the Devil; but was the Devil himſelf; though he appeared in Heaven, as you may ſee <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.13. and he it is, that has given Power to all thoſe, that have Perſecuted this Woman, or her Seed; but as long as he was in Heaven, he was no perfect Perſecutor; there he had no Power, but only to be an Accuſer of the Brethren, and therein he buſied himſelf Night and Day: But by this it is evident, that there was a Power over him, to which he accuſed them, and ſo long they could not ſing: but when he was caſt out with his Angels, then they ſung: Now is Salvation come, and Power, and the Kingdom of our God, and the Power of his Chriſt; for the Accuſer of our Brethren, that accuſed them Day and Night before our God, is caſt down, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But then wo unto them that dwell on Earth, where the Devil got his Power, that is in the Earthly Ground; there he Rules with great Wrath, Anger and Fury, and Indignation, Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting the Woman, and the leaſt appearance of her Seed; and becauſe he cannot do harm enough of himſelf, he goes and makes him a <hi>Subſtitute,</hi> to wit; a <hi>Beaſt</hi> with <hi>Seven Heads, and Ten Horns:</hi> Mark, juſt the Number of his own Heads and Horns; only he came out of the Pit, and this out of the Sea or Waters, of which Waters you may read in <hi>Revel.</hi> 15.17. <hi>That they are Peoples, Tongues, Languages, and Nations;</hi> and out of them came this ſtrange <hi>Beaſt,</hi> which the Devil counted worthy to have his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Power, becauſe he knew that he would do his Work for him to purpoſe; and he received his Power for the ſpace of 42. Moneths: And his firſt Work was, to Perſecute the Saints: Secondly, to ſet up the Worſhip of the Devil: Thirdly, to bring the dread of this ſeven Headed <hi>Beaſt</hi> over the whole Earth: Fourthly, To blaſpheme the Name of God, and his Tabernacle, and them that dwell therein: And fifthly to make People believe, that there is no overcoming of his Power: And theſe Works are ſpread, and carried on by three unclean Spirits, which came forth out of the mouth of the <hi>Dragon, Beaſt, and Falſe Prophet, over all Kindreds, Nations, Tongues and People, and there was none able to reſiſt them, except thoſe, whoſe Names were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Book of the Life of the Lamb.</hi> And as concerning them,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:31554:17"/> becauſe they would not receive the <hi>Mark of the Beaſt in their Fore-head, or Right-hand,</hi> They muſt be Baniſhed, and muſt not have Liberty to Buy or Sell; and thoſe that would Worſhip nothing but a Living Subſtance, and not an Image, though it was alive; thoſe muſt be killed, and when that Sort was all Killed and Baniſhed; and the whole World being brought, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to Worſhip the <hi>Dragon,</hi> ſometimes to Worſhip the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> that had ſo many <hi>Heads</hi> and <hi>Horns</hi> as the <hi>Dragon</hi> himſelf; and then to Worſhip a little <hi>Beaſt</hi> with two <hi>Horns,</hi> that came out of the Earth; and then to Worſhip the Image of the old ſeven Headed <hi>Beaſt:</hi> When I ſay, that all things upon the whole Earth were thus diſpoſed, then was it as the Devil would have it; for now had every one ſubjected himſelf unto his Power, and received that Name or Mark or the Number of the Subſtitute, and admired his great Power; and ſet him up as the chiefeſt among Men, whom none could overcome, except ſome few, that had the Word of God it ſelf (for the other had the Scripture) and durſt ſeal their Teſtimony againſt the <hi>Dragon</hi> and <hi>Falſe-Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> with their Blood; and becauſe theſe were but a few, and were ſoon killed; they being dead, there was a Joyfull and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry World; the Devil was well-pleaſed, and they did ſend their Gifts to one another abundantly; and thoſe that had been moſt buſie, and ſerviceable to kill the Witneſſes (that dared to ſpeak of another Kingdom or Dominion, beſides that of the <hi>Dragon</hi> and <hi>Beaſt</hi>) they had the greateſt Gifts. And in thoſe days there was no Propheſying, but in Sack-cloath, and that did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue long neither; but the Prophets were killed, and being Dead, their Dead Bodies were kept above the Earth, and were more eſteemed of, then their living Teſtimony was; for that plagued all the Worſhippers of the <hi>Beaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So, in ſuch a time have the Nations been ſo long, that they are ſo us'd to the Power and Raign of the Devil, that they plead for it; as if he had an undoubted Right thereunto: And if the Devil might ſpeak himſelf, he would not deſire of the World to rule any longer, then the World alloweth him: and they have forgot, that it is but to continue Forty two Moneths; whil'ſt the Man-Child was caught up unto God, and whil'ſt his Mother was in the Wilderneſs; and alſo, that it was to be expected,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:31554:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> that both ſhould appear again in their appointed time.</p>
            <p>But whil'ſt it was thus with the World (viz.) <hi>That the true Church was not to be found upon Earth; but was fled away, as upon</hi> Eagle's <hi>Wings; and that he, that ought to rule over all, was caught up into Heaven; and that the Devil was in his place, the old Serpent ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and giving his power to whom he pleaſed, to a Great Beast, or Little Beast, or to a Whore, or to any thing like him:</hi> And whil'ſt Great and Small, High and Low, Bond and Free, did wonder at his power, and were ready to worſhip any one that had his power, let thoſe, whoſe Eyes are open, but conſider in what a Lamentable State the miſerable World then was; and whether that Abomination, that made the World deſolate of God and all good Order, was not then ſet up in the Holy Place, where it ought not: And was the World without a Religion, or without a Profeſſion of God and Chriſt in thoſe dayes? No: they bore a Profeſſion of Chriſt, that is Unchangeable, in all their Change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able wayes; and this was a time of Gladneſs to many: and they had many ſorts of Religions; and when they came to be weary with one, the Devil furniſhed them with another. And when they had been exerciſed a long time in the aforeſaid Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips of the Dragon, the Seven-headed Beaſt, the Little Beaſt, and of the Living Image; then there came forth yet a deeper Myſtery of Iniquity then before, the Mother of all theſe Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination; ſhe ſhew'd her ſelf not as a deſpis'd Whore, but as a Queen decked with Scarlet, Purple, and Precious-Stones: and that very Beaſt, which none could over-come, but the whole World had wondred after it, he himſelf muſt be under her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and muſt carry her up and down upon the Waters; which are, Peoples, Lands, Tongues, and Languages. And this Whore hath another Deſign upon the poor blind World [Mark] She comes with a preparation to make all drunk, that they might not make uſe of their Sences, to bethink themſelves where they were; and that they might not have any ſuſpition againſt any thing, the furniſhes her ſelf with a Golden Cup, which there was none that had any thing againſt it, but every one could well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it; and this was but to deceive them; for, any Potſherd of the Dunghil had been good enough (yea, a Hog's Trough
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:31554:18"/> had been too good) to drink that out of, which ſhe had to give them. But ſhe muſt give her drink to Kings, and Princes, and Nobles, and Captains, and Merchants, and to all ſorts of men; ſo ſhe proffer'd them her Cup, and they have all drunk: But what have they drunk? Her Whoredoms, Fornications, and all Abominations of the Earth: How much? Till they were drunk: What did they then? They committed Fornication with her; they were drunk of Abominations; and the Whore was drunk of the Blood of the Saints and Witneſſes of Jeſus: and yet, the Name of Jeſus was ſtill profeſſed upon Earth; that was not perſecuted; but thoſe were perſecuted, that witneſſed Jeſus him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that takes away ſin, ſuch were perſecuted: For, ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Mother of Whores, and having nothing to proffer to her Cuſtomers but Abominations, ſhe could not endure to hear, That Sin, which is an Abomination to the Lord, ſhould be taken away; and that men ſhould live without ſin, and be perfect: For, if ſo, then ſhe muſt be Childleſs, and as a Widdow, and muſt loſe her High-place on the top of the Beaſt; and then they would not be ſo drunk of her Cup, and that would not tend to her Advantage; therefore if any came to be Witneſſes of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus himſelf, ſhe drunk the Blood of ſuch; but if they would be content to drink her Cup, and ſo would pleaſe themſelves with good and precious words, and in the mean time drink in her A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations, then they might live and flouriſh, as long as ſhe flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed.</p>
            <p>But Alas! What do you think, that read with Underſtanding was the ſtate of the World in thoſe dayes? Was it not high time that Plagues, Indignation and Vengeance ſhould be pour'd out upon this Bloody Whore, and upon the Seat of the Beaſt, upon which ſhe did ride, and upon the whole Earth, which had committed Fornication with her? Is it not high time that the Carpenters ſhould come, <hi>Zach.</hi> 1.20. to cut off theſe Horns? For at that time the power of Darkneſs was ſpread over all, and the will of the Devil was done, and his One Thouſand Two Hundred and Sixty Years were proſperous to his Kingdom; and he did what he pleaſed; and if any ſpoke againſt him, and againſt his kingdom, he would have them kill'd; and then his
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:31554:18"/> Whore would drink the Blood of ſuch; and there were none left, neither Great nor Small, neither Bond nor Free, High or Low, neither Young nor Old, but they had ſubmitted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves all of them; and ſaid, <hi>Who is like him? None are able to overcome him: It is impoſſible to be made free from under his power: He muſt raign as long as we live: it is poſſible for us</hi> (cry they) <hi>to overcome Princes, Kingdoms, and Armies; and therefore we go out, and fight valiantly, and many times we get Victory, and become Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors; but to overcome ſin, which the Devil has ſet up in us, that is impoſſible; and therefore it is in vain to trouble our ſelves about it; and we will not do any thing concerning it, ſeeing we have drunk in a Faith, That it is impoſſible to perform or accompliſh it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus has the whole World been bewitched, in the time when the Devil Raign'd: And will he and his Servants make us believe, That it muſt continue ſo alwayes? Though never any other time was given him, but ſuch as was limitted; and in the end of that time we underſtand there is a great Alteration to come to paſs, to wit, <hi>That the Church, the True Woman, muſt come out of the Wilderneſs again; the Man-Child muſt come down again, and appear upon Earth, and Rule the Nations with a Rod of Iron; and the Whore muſt be judged; that Sorrow, Death, and Famine muſt come upon her in one day; and that Ten Kings ſhould agree together, to burn her Fleſh with Fire; and that the Smoak of her Torments ſhould aſcend to Heaven; and then muſt the Dragon, the Beaſt, and falſe Prophet, that had ſtill preach'd Peace, though it was ſo, as above ſaid, they muſt all be taken, whil'ſt they are yet alive in this Work and in their Power, and be caſt into the Lake of the Wrath of God, which burneth forever; and theſe Princes, and Captains, and Merchants, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Earth muſt Howl and Lament becauſe of this great Alteration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore, ſeeing that ſuch a time is Lawfully to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, in which the Devil, the Old Serpent may be thruſt out of his dominion; and that then the time of Joy and Rejoycing will be for the Upright, it is worth the ſpending of our Labour and Time, to find out that Time; that ſo it may not come over us, and we ſee it not, nor know it not, and ſo let it paſs by, as the <hi>Jews</hi> did; and ſo doting and waiting for it, as a thing which is yet to come, as they do at this day; when almoſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:31554:19"/> Two Thouſand Years are paſt, ſince the thing is come to paſs.</p>
            <p>Now you know the <hi>Jews</hi> had a Prophet, which told them the time, when the Meſſiah ſhould come; aforehand, to wit, <hi>Daniel,</hi> as you may ſee, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.24. &amp;c. where he told them, That it was Seventy Weeks that were determin'd upon the People and upon the City, and that the Holy one ſhould be Anointed: Now this was not ſuch a great Myſtery to them; they knew it was common to reckon a day for a Year among the Prophets; ſo that that time was but four hundred fourſcore and ten years, that the Viſions ſhould be ſeal'd, and the daily Sacrifice taken away, the City be made deſolate and the Anointing of the Holy One, and the Meſſiah be ſlain for the ſins of the People: And ſince the time that the Command was gone forth to build <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> again, in which time the Seventy Weeks had their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; it is above Two Thouſand years ago, the City is ſince builded again, and alſo made again deſolate, and the daily Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice taken away; and the Prince of the People, that then came (viz.) <hi>Titus Veſpaſianus</hi> the <hi>Roman,</hi> has deſtroy'd the Sanctuary, and the Deſtruction of it was with an overflowing to the end of the War; and yet all theſe things cannot convince them, nor make them believe, that the Meſſiah is come, or that it was he, whom their Fore-fathers have killed as a Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer.</p>
            <p>Now, That We, after ſuch clear Propheſies of the ſetting up of the Kingdom of Chriſt, and diſ-throning of the Devil, Sin, and Antichriſt, ſhould not come to be ſurpriz'd with the ſame Blindneſs and Hardneſs of Heart; Let us have a ſtrict Obſervation of the Times, that we may not fight againſt the Appearance of Truth, and put it far away from us, and ſay, The Dayes are not come yet, in which the pouring out of the Spirit can be witneſſed; and that the Knowledge of God muſt cover the Earth, as the Waters cover the Sea; and that the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel muſt be preached again unto thoſe that dwell upon the Earth; and that the Lamb and his Saints muſt have the Victory over the Dragon and his Angels: For, ſuch as put the Day ſo far from them, are in one and the ſame Error with the <hi>Jews,</hi> and do not underſtand the Times better then they do; and ſo are perſecute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:31554:19"/> the true appearance of that, which they ſeem to expect, and to pray for (as the <hi>Jewes</hi> did) becauſe it does not appear in their Way, to anſwer their Carnal expectations, that deſpiſe the day of ſmall things: But from ſuch are the Myſteries of the Kingdom ſhut up; and are revealed unto thoſe that fear the Lord.</p>
            <p>Now to underſtand theſe things, let every one come to read the Propheſies in a meaſure of that Spirit, by which they were given forth, and that ſame opens the Propheſies, and without it every one underſtands only according to his own Fancy, or private Judgment: The Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>There ſhould come an Apoſtacy from the Faith;</hi> that is, from the true Chriſtian Faith: Now, when was that? And who are they that are thus Apoſtatized, or fallen away? Ask the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the whole <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Church, and they will tell you, that the Propheſie points at <hi>Martin Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Zuinglius, Aecolampadius, Calvinus, Menno Simoni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and other Hereticks, that have rent many Nations from the true Apoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith, and the Ancient Chriſtian Church, the infallible Foundation and Pillar of Truth, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Ask the <hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>Presbyters</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> the Pfarrherren or <hi>Paſtors</hi> in <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Sweed-Land,</hi> and <hi>Predicants</hi> in the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> and they will tell you, that this Propheſie ſignifieth the general Apoſtacy from the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith and Order in the Church of Chriſt, to the <hi>Pope</hi> and Popiſh Exerciſes, and Inſtitutions over all Chriſtendom. Again, ask them; Which among themſelves continue as yet in the true Apoſtolical Faith and Religion? Then the <hi>Lutheran Paſtors</hi> will ſay, that are we, and therefore cry they, Joyn with us. No, ſay the <hi>Biſhops</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> we will prove that the Apoſtolical Church had <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and that the Apoſtle ſaid; He that deſires the Office of a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> he deſires a good Work; and therefore We are they, that are the true Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch according to the firſt Inſtitution. Then ſayes the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Dutch Predicants;</hi> The <hi>Biſhops</hi> in the Primitive Churches were not ſuch as you are, but ſuch as we are, whoſe ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e was over the Flock, and did Teach, and Rule in Eccleſiaſtical Matters, but not in Councels and Parliaments, as you do; therefore you are fallen from the Primitive ſtate. And now at laſt what ſayes <hi>Truth</hi> of theſe, and all others, who deny that Faith, which Purifies
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:31554:20"/> the Heart, and can Cleanſe the Conſcience from Sin, and can give Victory over the World? This was the Faith which <hi>Paul</hi> Preached, that was nigh, in the Heart; and therefore all thoſe that ſay, that the Heart of a true Believer cannot be made clean; nor that he can come to live without Sin; nor to have a Purified Conſcience; And all thoſe that denyes the Word of Faith in the Heart, and Chriſt to be the Rule, and ſet up another Rule, and another Faith, and another Foundation for it, then the Apoſtle ſet up; all ſuch are fallen from the Faith, and are not Apoſtolick, but Antichriſtian; and when the Man of Sin comes to be revealed, they will come to be revealed with him, and fall with him, and with <hi>Babylon</hi> the Mother of them all; and great will be their fall in that day.</p>
            <p>There is yet another Propheſie of Chriſt, when he ſaid, <hi>When you ſee the Abomination of Deſolation ſtanding in the Holy Place, where it ought not; then let not him that is in</hi> Judea <hi>flee upon the Mountaines; Nor he that is in the Field, go back to fetch his Cloathes: And he that is on the Houſe top, come down to take any thing out of his Houſe, &amp;c. Mat.</hi> 24.15 and ſaid he further, <hi>verſ.</hi> 23, 24. <hi>Then if any Man ſhall ſay unto you, Lo here is Chriſt, or there, believe him not, &amp;c.</hi> ſignifying plainly, that when the Abomination of Deſolation ſhould be ſet up, that the People would notwithſtanding not want divers ſorts of Teachers of the Name of Chriſt. What were they made deſolate of by the ſetting up of this Abomination, ſeeing they were not deſolate of a profeſſion of Chriſt in divers manners? They were deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late of the Power and Preſence of God in all their Holy Places, (as they called them) where this Abomination was ſet up; even as Chriſt ſaid to the <hi>Jewes,</hi> when they had made the Houſe of prayer to be a Den of Thieves; then ſaid he, <hi>your Houſe is left unto you deſolate.</hi> Mark, it was not then deſolate of People, of Congregations, of Religions and Worſhips; but it was deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late of the Preſence of God; for that was not to be found there. So that Abomination, which makes People deſolate of the Power of God, by which they ſhould have power over their Sin and Luſts; and which make the Miniſters and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers deſolate of the Spirit of God, by which they ſhould have been led to Preach the Goſpel; this Abomination has been ſet
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:31554:20"/> up a long time, and made the People and Nations as a Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and this has been ſince that time, that the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion has been carried on and maintained by the Traditions of Men; <hi>Then came the Poyſon to be poured out into the Church,</hi> and thereby it is come to be ſo ſwell'd and bigg, that it can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend in it the Tyrannical and perſecuting Princes, Proud and Rebellious <hi>Biſhops,</hi> wicked Man-ſlayers and Murderers, Unclean, Wanton and Drunken People; they have all room enough in it: and ſince that time it is counted Hereſie, that any ſhould make a profeſſion of being Purified and Cleanſed; and from that time it may be reckoned, that the Abomination of Deſolation has been ſet up: And therefore let us conſider how long it is yet to ſtand, before the Devil come to be caſt out, and the Temple of God be Cleanſed, and the filth of Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination be burn'd up, that the God of Heaven may again de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in his Sanctuary, and that the Earth may not for ever be empty of his preſence, but that he may be found of thoſe that ſeek him, and be heard of them that are Mourning after him.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>John</hi> ſaith, that this time of Deſolation was to continue a Time, Times, and half a Time, that is, three years and a half, or three times twelve Moneths and ſix Moneths, that is 42. Moneths, or 1260 Dayes; which times are agreeing together in one, and do perfectly fulfill the time of the reſtoration of the Church, and of the coming down of the Righteous Judge, whoſe right it is to Rule over Men; for to him are the <hi>Gentiles</hi> given for an Inheritance, and the ends of the Earth for a poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And that time doth alſo perfectly fulfill the time of the Power of the Beaſt; for theſe times do all agree together, and as they had their beginning about one and the ſame time, they muſt alſo have their end ſhortly after one another, becauſe they are like one another.</p>
            <p>Now to find out the end of thoſe times, the beginning muſt be firſt known; now the daily Sacrifice was taken away long before the Abomination, that made the Earth deſolate, was ſet up; but from that time, that both ſhould be fulfilled, ſaid the Angel to <hi>Daniel,</hi> ſhould there be 1290 Dayes, that is 30. more then <hi>John</hi> writes of: Now the Abomination of Deſolation was
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:31554:21"/> not ſet up in the time of Chriſt; for ſaid he, <hi>When you ſhall ſee it ſet up, &amp;c.</hi> ſpeaking as of a thing that was not yet come to paſs; and the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>There ſhall come an Apoſtacy from the Faith;</hi> that ſhews, that it was not yet come, neither did it come till ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>veral hundreds of years after; for the true Chriſtians ſuffered many cruel and grievous deaths for the Chriſtian Faith; ſo that they did not fall away, but endured to the end, and were ſaved, and ſo long the Earth was not Deſolate: But when that Faith was loſt, which did ſupport in Sufferings, and that the <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> (which was the holy Place) came to be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by Pride, Covetouſneſs, Perſecution and Worldly Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, Eaſe, and the Delights and Honours of this World; then the Abomination was ſet up, that made the Earth Deſolate: And reckon from that time 1260 Years, and add to it theſe 30. Years, of which the Angel ſpoke to <hi>Daniel, Dan.</hi> 12.11. and ſee whether we be not about the Forty Five Years, of which there is made mention in the 12th verſe, where the Angel having ſpoken of the 1290. years, adds, <hi>Bleſſed is he that waiteth, and cometh to the Thouſand Three Hundred and Thirty Five Dayes:</hi> Signifying plainly, that there muſt be a time of Patience and Waiting for the Bleſſed Reſtauration, which was promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; and that that time of Waiting ſhould continue from the 1290. till 1335. which are 45. dayes or years; and then they are Bleſſed that come thereunto. So he that hath Wiſdom let him reckon: But this Reckoning is not comprehended in Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metick, or the Art of Reckoning; neither can it be conceiv'd by the Wiſdom of this World; But ſuch as have the Wiſdom, which cometh from God, they ſhall underſtand; and it is to ſuch I write; for, I have learn'd to cover the Pearls before the Swine, and to with-hold the Children's Bread from the Dogs.</p>
            <p>And by what is here ſaid, it ſufficiently appears, Firſt, That this Intruder or Uſurper, call'd the Devil, Satan, Dragon, or Antichriſt, has no Right to Rule and to Rain over Mankind all the dayes of their Life. Secondly, That his Kingdom is a limited Kingdom, and was not to continue forever. Thirdly- That the limits of it has been reveal'd to ſeveral of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God. Fourthly, That the appointed time of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is nigh come to an End. Fifthly, That there is a Bleſſed
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:31554:21"/> Day and Time to be expected after the end of his Raign. And Sixthly, That none can come to enjoy that Bleſſed Time and Bleſſedneſs, nor ſing the Song of Joy and Deliverance, but thoſe that patiently wait upon the Lord in the dayes of Tribulation; and have that Hope to ſee the Salvation, which cometh out of <hi>Sion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore, for a Concluſion, I ſhall ſay this, That all thoſe that feel themſelves in Bondage under this Prince of Darkneſs, in what manner ſoever it be, and are not willing to remain ſo alwayes; Believe but in him, that ſheweth you your Bondage, and wait in his pure Light in your own Conſciences, which diſcovers Darkneſs, and the Prince of it; and then you will feel a Hope to ſpring up in you, that you may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd, as I my ſelf have felt:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.3.</note> And this Hope will lead to a daily Waſhing and Purifying, and to a daily Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying and Mortifying of thy earthly Members: And as this Hope comes to work in thee, it will bring thee to an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of being deliver'd in ſome particular things, and that will ſtrengthen thy Hope of being deliver'd from more; and ſo, at laſt a Faith will ariſe in thee, Perfectly and Thorowly to be made free from ſin: And when thou art made Partaker of this Faith, then the greateſt and ſtrongeſt Bond of the Devil is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; for, through the Unbelief of it he keeps his Kingdom in Man and Woman: And when this Evil Root of Unbelief is taken away, then his Kingdom comes ſoon to an end, and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Truth comes to be ſet up in thee; and ſo there comes a Change to he wrought in thee, both inwardly and outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and ſo comes his Kingdom, who is the Intruder or Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, to be leſſen'd, firſt, in thy ſelf, and then thou comeſt to ſee that Change in another; and ſo it goeth forward, from one to ten, and from ten to a thouſand, and ſo forth, more and more, until the Inheritance of the Wicked comes to be wholy laid waſte; till Truth and Righteouſneſs, and the Raign and Government of Chriſt Jeſus our Lord comes to be ſet up in the Earth, which my Soul longs and travels for; and ſo, I know, it is with many more, for whoſe ſake this is written; and as a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:31554:22"/> againſt that proud and preſumptious Generation of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, of what Sort or Name, or in what Nation or King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſoever they may be, who not only have ſubjected them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unto this Prince of Darkneſs, and unto the Power of him who is call'd the Devil, and Satan; but alſo pretend, That all Mankind muſt do ſo, and continue ſo all their dayes, and that there is no Remedy nor Help againſt it; and ſo deny the Power of God, and lead the people to truſt in a Lye: But the Day of the Power of God is come, and the Refuge of Lyes is ſwept away; and the Deliverance and Victory of the Lamb is known unto many; to whom, and to the Everlaſting God, by the Operation of the Holy Spirit in the Hearts of the Redeemed be ſung Everlaſting Praiſes, Thankſ-giving, Renown, Honour and Glory, and Dominion forever</p>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
               <p>THere comes ſomething further up in my Heart concerning this matter, which I think good to communicate unto you.</p>
               <p>There are hardly any ignorant, how commonly it is ſaid, That we cannot live without ſin; and that we cannot be made free from it, as long as we live in this World; even as if our Sin and our Life were ſo knit together, that they cannot be ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from one another; but that they muſt end together, and not the one before the other. Now all thoſe that believe there is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> God, they alſo believe, that he is the Fountain of Life, and gives Life unto all that Lives: And all that believes that there is a Devil, they alſo believe, that he is the Author and Original of Sin; as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>When he ſpeaks a Lye, he ſpeaks of his own; for he is a Lyar, and a Father of Lyes,</hi> Joh. 8.44. and ſo he is of all other Wickedneſs: Now he gives life to no man; for that comes of God; and he having made them live, then comes the Devil,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:31554:22"/> and betrayes them unto ſin: And now are Men and Women be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſuch Fools, that they ſeek to bind together inſeparably that which is of God, with that which is of the Devil; and that is a gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Fooliſhneſs: For, What Fellowſhip has Chriſt with <hi>Belial,</hi> or Light with Darkneſs? So alſo the Life of Men (ſimply con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd in it ſelf) has no Fellowſhip with ſin; for they come forth of two different Originals; and he, who is the Original of Life, is ſtronger then he, who is the Original of Sin: And though he has brought in Sin, and has corrupted Nature (which firſt was pure) by ſin; and men, in that corrupt Nature, do abuſe their Life, which they have from God, to his Diſhonour, and to their own Perdition; yet that Life is not ſo joyn'd unto Sin, that they are inſeparable: For, though it be true, That men cannot ſin, if they live not; yet it is not true to ſay, That if men ſin not, then they cannot live; for the life that ſome lived, they lived by the Faith of the Son of God, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. and that is in dominion over Sin, and over the Devil the Author of it.</p>
               <p>There is another common Poſition, <hi>That we muſt live in ſin ſo long as we do carry about with us this Body of Sin and Death; meaning this Subſtantial or Corporal Body; alledging the words of</hi> Paul, Rom. 7.24.</p>
               <p>Now this is alſo a Blind and Fooliſh Poſition, as if the Fault of all ſins which they commit, were in the Body, or the Member<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of it; whereas on the contrary the Body (ſimply in it ſelf) is not guilty of that which through the Body is done, it being altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſſive, having no will in the Members; but they are as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, that are order'd or diſpos'd of according to the Laws of God, or of the Devil; the one or the other being ſet up to rule in the Will and Mind of the Creature; and the Members have no power to do, or leave undone any thing, but as they receive it by the Will or Underſtanding.</p>
               <p>Alſo there is no Member of the Body, but is made to ſerve the Lord, and is alſo made fit for it; and they are as ready and willing to do, and to fulfil the Will of God, as to fulfil the will of the Devil; yea, and they are more properly in their right place and ſervice, and have more joy and freedom in it, then in the ſervice of the Devil; for the ſervice of the Devil is but Bondage; to which the Creature is led captive by a Lye, as is afore ſaid,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:31554:23"/> and thoſe that call the Corporal Bodies the Bodies of Sin and Death, they pleaſe the Devil well enough; for he well knows that as long as they ſo Believe, his Birth and Seed will remain in them without hinderance, when the Eyes of Men are led out to ſuſpect their own Bodies, as being the cauſe of all Sin and Evil which they commit; which Bodies are more fit to ſerve God; but are capable to be given up by the Will and Affection to ſerve either God, or the Devil; as is manifeſt by the words of <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 6.19. <hi>As ye have yeelded your ſelves Servants to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, and to Iniquity unto Iniquity; even ſo now yeeld your Members Servants to Righteouſneſs unto Holineſs;</hi> Now here every one may ſee, that the ſame Members, that before were given up to ſerve Unrighteouſneſs, muſt now be given up to ſerve Righteouſneſs [Mark] they had them ſtill, they did not ſay, we would we were delivered from theſe Members and Bodies (that were uſed to commit Sin) that ſo we might come to be made free: But the Apoſtle ſaid plainly, <hi>That they were free from Sin, and were become Servants unto Righteouſneſs,</hi> and that therefore they ſhould give up their Members to the Service of him, that had made them free; as formerly they uſed to do to him that had brought them into Bondage: And th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe People that ſo complain againſt their own Bodies, calling them the old Man, the Body of Sin and Death, and of Corruption; How will they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Apoſtle, where he ſayes, <hi>Mortifie your Members which are upon the Earth?</hi> What, will they Mortifie their Hands and Feet, and pull out their Eyes, and cut out their Tongues? I ſuppoſe not; But how will they fulfill the words of the Apoſtle, except they find out another Body of Sin, and the Members of it, which ought to be crucified with the daily Croſs? But the Apoſtle hath named the Members of that Body, which muſt be Mortified, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.5. to wit, <hi>Fornication, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs Inordinate Affection, Evil Concupiſcence and Covetouſneſs, which is Idolatry, verſ.</hi> 8. <hi>Anger, Wrath, Malice, Blaſphemy, filthy Communication out of your Mouth, and lying one to another, &amp;c.</hi> theſe are the Members, that make up that Body which is called the Body of the Sins of the Fleſh, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11. and this is a ſort of Fleſh which God has not made; for that which he hath made, that is good, and it is for himſelf, and not for Sin, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.13. and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:31554:23"/> though the Devil hath his ſeat in the Heart, commanding the Members of the Body to do his will; yet the ſame Members could ſerve to do the Will of God, if the Devil were caſt out, and Truth and Righteouſneſs were ſet up in the Heart; and then theſe Sin-pleaders would come to ſee, that the fault was not in their Bodies, but in their corrupt Hearts, and that there is another Body to be put off, before they can come to do the will of God, and not the Corporal Body, which God has Created to ſerve him.</p>
               <p>And beſides that, theſe People ſhew themſelves to have but little love to God; that all his kindneſs and manifold Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies cannot draw them to ſerve him, but on the contrary they will ſerve his greateſt Enemy, as long as they have Members to ſerve him withall, uſing thoſe Members which God has given them, againſt him and his ordering; and if he will not permit it ſo to be, he muſt take away thoſe Members again; even as if there was no other remedy to put an end to ſin; that is as much as to ſay, If the Lord will not have them to Swear, to Lye, or to ſpake Evil; he muſt make them Dumb; and if he will not have them to do bad Works, he muſt make them Lame, and if he will take away their Life from them, then they will leave off ſinning, but not ſooner: yea, they cannot endure to hear of putting off of Sin ſooner; <hi>That (ſay they) is the Grand Error of the Quakers,</hi> to ſpeak of ceaſing to Sin, before we ceaſe to live.</p>
               <p>O! Where is the ſence of the Love of God, that this People ſhould feel in their Hearts ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> abroad to God, to conſtrain them unto Obedience? Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> They are ſtrangers thereunto, and the Covenant with Hell an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>th is ſo ſtrong, and the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief is ſo rooted in them, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ey think, this Covenant can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be broken: But Bleſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Lord; that Faith is now manifeſted, that giveth Victory, and breaketh this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
               <p>Another great Plea, which theſe Sin-pleaders bring, is this, If People can come to Perfection in this Life, then they have no need of Chriſt to be their Saviour; as if the Salvation by Chriſt; and a Perfect and pure Life were Inconſiſtant with one another: You fools, and blind, Know ye not that all
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:31554:24"/> good and Perfect Gifts come from the Lord; and that none can come to Perfection, but by his Gift? and if God be the giver, Is it not then by Grace? Where are Works then? but theſe Pleaders for Sin are as great ſtrangers to the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is in Chriſt Jeſus, as they are to Perfection; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they would ſee their Ignorance: When Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples; Be ye Perfect, as your Father which is in Heaven is Perfect: that is, as much as to ſay, (according to the expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of theſe People) There is your Command, when that is done, you have no need of me: And the Apoſtle ſpoke <hi>Wiſdom among them that were Perfect,</hi> but not ſuch wiſdom (or rather fooliſhneſs) as this, to perſwade them, that they had no need of Chriſt to be their Saviour, becauſe they were come to Perfection; but on the contrary he ſaid; That he could do all things (then he could be Perfect) but not as of himſelf; but through Chriſt that enabled him: and thoſe that come to a Perfect State, they know that their Salvation is not of their Works, how good and pure ſoever they may be, but meerly by Grace through Jeſus Chriſt; and that in reſpect of theſe three following Obſervations.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, That it was the Appearance of Chriſt Jeſus, who is the Power of God, that has brought them off from their Sin and Imperfection; and that they have not left them off of themſelves, but do own that it is the Grace of God, as the Apoſtle did, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2 11, 12. <hi>For the Grace of God that bringeth Salvation hath appeared unto all Men; Teaching us, that denying <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs and Worldly Luſts, we ſhould live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent World.</hi> So here you may ſee, that it is the Appearance of the Grace of God, that leads to Perfection, and this Perfection is not yet a perfect Salvation; for thoſe that have it, may fall from it again, and ſo not be ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ved; but thoſe that endure to the end ſhall be ſaved.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But Secondly, it is Chriſt, who is the Preſerver and Keeper unto the end of thoſe that truſt in him; and the Apoſtles teſtifie that thoſe, that were Delivered from the corruption of this World, muſt know him to be their Keeper, that had gathered them out of the World; and therefore ſaid <hi>Jude</hi> in his Epiſtle verſ. 24. <hi>Now unto him that is able to keep you from fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and to Preſent you faultleſs before the Preſence of his Glory with exceeding joy, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Petter</hi> teſtifieth, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. <hi>You are kept by the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:31554:24"/> Power of God through Faith unto Salvation, ready to be Revealed in the laſt Time.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifieth, <hi>That the keeping is by Jeſus Chriſt, Phil.</hi> 4.7. So here you may ſee, that the bringing to the ſtate of Perfection, and the keeping from falling from it again, is both the Work of Chriſt; and yet this is not a perfect Salvation; fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this does not put away the former Sins.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But thirdly, Whoever comes to perfect Salvation, he comes to know Chriſt to be an Offering for Sin, and to obtain Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with God, and forgiveneſs of his former ſins: For all the holy Converſation, and perfection of Life can be counted no more, but his Duty; and therefore he cannot obtain remiſſion of one of his former Sins; but thoſe that confeſs their ſins, and forſake them, ſuch comes to forgiveneſs by Jeſus Chriſt, and comes to know his Blood clenſing them from all their former Sins; and ſo they come to perfect Salvation by Grace, not by Works, but by Faith, that works in the Love of God, unto Obedience, without which, Faith is but dead, and makes no man ſaved; but thoſe that have this true Faith and Hope in them, <hi>They purifie themſelves, as he is Pure,</hi> 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 3.3. and he that has not this Hope, does not purifie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, neither does he believe, that he can do it; and by this we know the true Believers from the falſe; and by this Sinners are made manifeſt, that cannot ſtand in the Congregation of the Righteous, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.5.</p>
               <p>So now let all the <hi>Pleaders for Sin</hi> ſtop their Mouthes for ever; and let the Devil ſtand for himſelf, and plead his own cauſe; and henceforth do not deſpiſe and revile the Innocent, (that are tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling and ſtriving after Perfection, with a Faith to obtain it) that they think to be ſaved by their own works; for we hope for no other <hi>Salvation,</hi> but that which is in and by Jeſus Chriſt the Eternal Son of God, who is the Firſt-born of every Creature, that brings many Sons and Daughters unto Glory; but not by leaving them in their ſins; but his Name is <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and he <hi>ſaves People from their Sins.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>S. C.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:31554:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31554:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
